Tomas Resendiz

E-mail: tomas.resendiz@icloud.com | Address: Austin, TX LinkedIn: https://www.linkedin.com/in/tomas-resendiz/

GitHub: https://github.com/nomadtomas

Career Summary

Former statistician for the USDA National Agricultural Statistics Service. Experience with Data Analysis, Machine Learning, Interpreting Results, Experiment Design, Extract Data Sets from Databases, Report Data, and Querying. Possess strong analytical skills. An insatiable learner who loves self-improvement and tackling new challenges. I also possess strong ability to work both independently and with a team.

Technical Skills

Tools: Python, PySpark, R, SQL, noSQL, Excel, VBA, Docker

Data Manipulation & Visualization: pandas, matplotlib, seaborn, Tableau, Power BI

Machine Learning: scikit learn, tensorflow, NLP Database: MySQL, PostgreSQL, mongoDB, Access

Language: English – native, Spanish – native, Portuguese – intermediate

Relevant Experience

Statistician June 2009 – January 2020

USDA-National Agricultural Statistics Service

Austin, TX

Spearheaded and developed a new methodology and program to improve commodity estimation and forecasting using VBA and Python. Coordinate and monitor regional survey implementation and trainings. Developed tools to optimize and improve consistency of repetitive tasks using VBA and Python. | *Key Accomplishments*:

- > Develop framework and pipeline to provide reliable numbers about the different varieties of wheat.
- Establish visualization methods and dashboards for state and regional analysis.
- Managed statewide survey implementations on-time and within budgets.
- Developed multiple VBA, ArcGIS, and Python programs to streamline data reconciliation and data analysis.

Economic Development Officer

U.S. Peace Corps

August 2010 – November 2011

Katwe, Uganda

Helped develop Business models, SWOT analysis, financial reporting, and 5-year business plans for small community businesses. Became liaison between local governments and private businesses. | *Key Accomplishments*:

- Developed community marketing and outreach programs for Eco-Tourism enterprises.
- Authored MoUs between local businesses and local governments.
- > Created and executed Public-Private Partnerships (PPP), grant writing, marketing, and business management trainings.

Congressional Liaison

January 2007 – May 2007

U.S. Congress

Washington D.C

Worked as a liaison to the Congressional Hispanic Caucus. Advocated for and promoted legislation for the betterment of Hispanic and Latino social issues and empowerment. | *Key Accomplishments:*

- Recipient of a Congressional Award for Distinguish and Outstanding Service.
- Generated co-sponsorship support from multiple congressional members on various legislation authored by Congressman Cuellar.
- Increased network contacts both in the public and private sector.

Education

Galvanize Data Science Bootcamp: Austin, TX

Galvanize is a dynamic learning community that offers top-notch courses in data science. I was a student in the Data Science Immersive program. Key areas of study focus:

- ➤ 600 hours of training in data science, data engineering, database management, and general computer science.
- Programming: Python, Scikit-Learn, Numpy, Pandas, Scipy.stats
- Statistics: A/B testing, Multi-arm Bandit, Hypothesis Testing, Linear Regression, Logistic Regression
- Machine Learning: Random Forest, Naive Bayes, kNN, kMeans, Hierarchical Clustering, t-SNE, PCA, SVD, NMF, Gradient Boosting
- > Deep Learning: Keras, Tensorflow, Word2Vec, Doc2Vec
- Database Management: Postgres SQL, MongoDB
- Web Scraping: JSON, Beautifulsoup, Selenium
- Data Visualization: Matplotlib, Pandas, Bokeh, Seaborn, Plotly
- Web Design: Flask, HTML, CSS
- Natural Language Processing (NLP): NLTK, Gensim, Topic Modeling, Sentiment Analysis

Bootcamp Certificate: University of Texas, Austin, TX

Jan. 2019-Jul. 2019

Dec. 2019-Mar. 2020

Through an immersive 24 intensive weeks of fundamentals of data analytics and visualization. This program enhanced my knowledge of many key fundamental concepts of data analytics. Key areas of study focus:

- Excel Functions: Pivot tables, VBA Scripting, Advance functions
- Fundamental Statistics: Modeling, Forecasting, and Regression analysis
- > Python Programming: Python 3, NumPy, pandas, Matplotlib, API Interactions
- Databases: MySQL, PostgresSQL, MongoDB, ETL
- Front End Web Visualization: HTML, CSS, Bootstrap, Dashboarding, JS Charting, D3.js, Geomapping with Leaflet.js
- > Business Intelligence Software: Tableau
- Advanced Topics: Big Data Analytics with Hadoop, Machine Learning

Texas Tech University Jan. 2010-May 2013

College of Agricultural Science and Natural Resources | Master of Agribusiness.

Universidade Federal do Rio Grande do Sul - UFRGS

Jan. 2010-Jul 2010

Porto Alegre, Brazil | Study abroad program

Texas Tech University Aug. 2005-Dec. 2009

College of Agricultural Science and Natural Resources | Agricultural and Applied Economics, B.S.

Korea University Aug. 2008-June 2009

Seoul, South Korea | Study abroad program